# 大家好 家裡的菜刀都有點鈍啦
Hi everyone! My kitchen knife at home is a bit blunt,
# 沒有那個磿刀石
but I don't have a sharpening stone.
# 我到那個河邊 檢一個磿刀石
We're gonna pick one from the, you know, the riverside.
# 嗯 這個針草(註︰這個「針草」不像是網上找到的「鬼針草」，隨便取個名字算了)
Um! This is "needle grass".
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 好深啊 這個
It's so deep here.
# 像這個就可以呀
A stone like this one is good enough.
# 不過太小啦 我們要找一個大的
But it's too small. We're gonna find a big one.
# 你看
Look!
# 一磿就可以把那個粉磨出來 (註︰這裡應該說是磿刀時把鋼粉磿出來)
Then, the steel dust can be ground out,
# 哇 是不是
Wa! Right?
# 那刀磿得很利的
The knife can be made really sharp.
# 要找個大的
I gotta find a big one.
# 難找哦
That's not easy, though.
# 好多魚呀
There are a lot of small fish.
# 都在撞到我腳上來啦
They're all bumping onto my feet.
# 也有大魚喲
I can see some big fish too.
# 有個
Here's one!
# 你看
Look!
# 這檢了一個
So I've picked one.
# 呃 這個有用的
Eh! This one is good.
# 拿回家哦 拿回家去
Let's bring it back, bring it back home.
# 把我那張菜刀磿利一點
I gotta sharpen my kitchen knife.
# 看一下還有沒有
Let's see if I can find another one.
# 好成事雙 多檢一個
Good things should come in pair. So one more.
# 沒啦 就一個
This is the only one. No more.
# 一個也好
One is already good enough.
# 回家 吃午飯
Let's go back home, for lunch,
# 磿一個那個刀 (註︰不知為何，這樣譯法好像更順耳，但文法卻不對)
and sharpen the knife.
# 你看 這鐵屑都磿出來啦
Look! This steel dust is already coming out.
# 好啦 磿好啦
Alright! Done!
# 隨便削就削掉啦 好利呀
It can simply be peeled. The knife is so sharp now.
# 我去 菜園裡面看一下 有甚麼好切的
Let me, have a look at the veggie garden and see if there's anything good.
# 切一點回來
I'll come back with some.
# 鴨子
Duckies!
# 小雞
Chickens!
# 你看 這兄弟家的菜園哦
Look! This is my buddy's veggie garden.
# 蘿蔔也老啦
The radish is already getting old,
# 青菜也老啦
and the veggies too.
# 啥都沒有
Nothing good.
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 兄弟家的雞
My buddy's chickens.
# 跑那麼快
They're running so fast.
# 你看 這個 這個 這個可以吃的 這個
Look! This, this, this can be dished up. I mean this,
# 這個棕樹
this palm,
# 棕樹花
palm flowers.
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 怎麼回事
What happens?
# 那麼多雞跑出來
So many chickens are running out!
# 我把這個棕樹把它搞下來
I'm gonna get the palm flowers, get them down.
# 這個炒 炒肉很好吃的哦 這個
It tastes really good when it's fried, fried with meat.
# 拿梯子來
I need a ladder.
# 你看 這個兄弟家的梯子
Look! This is my buddy's ladder.
# 借用一下啊
Let's borrow it.
# 你看 這兄弟家的雞窩哦
Look! This is my buddy's chicken coop.
# 他都不養雞
But he doesn't have any chickens.
# 下次我買兩隻雞來 放在這裡
I'll buy two chickens next time, and bring them here.
# 嗯 這樣就可以啦
Um! It's alright now.
# 嘿
Hey!
# 下來
Get down!
# 剛剛好 這個
Perfect! And this one.
# 這個也可以砍掉它
This one can be chopped off too.
# 你看 這個很漂亮的哦
Look! It's so beautiful, isn't it?
# 這個
It's like...
# 你看 也很 很嫩 這個開了的很嫩
Look! It's re, really young, it's really young inside.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個就 還沒有怎麼開 比較嫩一點 這個
And this is, it has not really blossomed, and it's rather young.
# 這個就穩微老一點 它的很多的開花啦
This one is a bit old. There are already many flowers.
# 這個就沒有
But not this one.
# 你看
Look!
# 那個粉 粉艷色 那個顏色那麼鮮艷
That's pink, shocking pink. The colour is so bright.
# 這個桃花很漂亮的哦
This peach flowers are really pretty.
# 我去看一下
Let me take a look.
# 你都沒見過這種桃花
I've never seen this kind of peach flowers before.
# 你看 這個是我前年放的香菇哦
Look! These are the shiitake mushrooms that I put two years ago.
# 現在有一點點 木頭都腐蝕掉啦
There's a tiny little bit of mushrooms. The wood is already rotten.
# 等下晚上我 過來把它摘啦 現在沒帶袋子
I'll come and pick them tonight. I don't have a bag with me now.
# 等一下來
I'll come again.
# 桃花朵朵開
Peach flowers are everywhere.
# 你看 這個桃花
Have a look at the peach flowers.
# 這裡長了兩棵桃花
Here are two peach flowers.
# 很漂亮的哦 這種桃花
The flowers are really pretty!
# 我記住它啦
I'll bear this in my mind.
# 下次我有桃子的時候 就直接來摘
Where there are peaches, I'll coming and pick them right away.
# 這個 不知道是不是誰家的 應該是野生的
This is, I wonder if if belongs to anyone. I think it's wild.
# 那個顏色那麼鮮艷
The colour is really bright.
# 普通的桃花好像沒那麼鮮艷 哦
It seems to be so much brighter than ordinary peach flowers, am I right?
# 桃子應該很好吃
The peaches must be very tasty.
# 這個 這種桃子
The, I mean this kind of peaches.
# 花都開得那麼漂亮
It has really pretty flowers.
# 桃子也應該也很靚
And so it must have really beautiful peaches.
# 肯定很好吃
Certainly, the taste must be wonderful too.
# 我還小的時候 我爺爺跟我說
When I was still a kid, my grandpa told me,
# 站在桃花樹上
that standing on a peach tree,
# 在桃花樹下
I mean under a peach tree,
# 搖一下這個桃花
then shake off the peach flowers,
# 拿去桃花運的哦
brings you "peach luck" (brings you a new lover).
# 哎喲 忘記啦
Ayo! I've forgotten,
# 我都是有婦之夫啦
that I'm already somebody's husband.
# 不好意思
I'm sorry,
# 把你搖啦
for having shaken you.
# 這樣 把這個切碎
So, I cut it into pieces.
# 像個魚蛋一樣 這個 (註︰他應該是指魚的卵)
It looks like fish eggs, isn't it?
# 先把這個過一下水
I'll boil it in water first,
# 用開水煮一下 然後再來炒
boil it in hot water first, and the fry it.
# 把這個水燒燙 把這個倒下去
I'll pour it into the water when the water starts boiling.
# 過一下水
then boil it for a while.
# 就等於說把它的那個澀味呀 把它去掉
It's like, to remove the astringent taste in the flowers.
# 有點澀澀的 (註︰不想太重覆"Astringent"這個字)
It might taste a bit funny otherwise.
# 火力不夠猛
The fire isn't strong enough.
# 稍等一下
A moment
# 這個水燙啦 把這個放下去
The water is boiling now. Let me put it in,
# 煮一下
and boil it for a while.
# 哇
Wa!
# 好香啊
It smells so good!
# 那種香味
The fragrance...
# 把這個 撈起來
Let me, scoop it out.
# 把這個洗一下
I wash it first.
# 多搞點油
Put some more oil.
# 把這豬肉放下去
I now put the pork into the wok.
# 再把這個
And then,
# 再把這個順便放下去
and then the flowers too.
# 啊 放點鹽
Ah! Put some salt,
# 多放點
more salt,
# 放香一點(註︰?????這是甚麼意思)
so that it smells better.
# 摘點水
Get some water.
# 加點水
Put some water.
# 搞幾個泡椒下去
Why don't we put some pickled peppers?
# 加點這個醬油
Put some soy sauce.
# 啊 好啦
Ah! Alright!
# 關火
Off the fire.
# 看下 這個
Have a look at this one.
# 可以喲 看上去
It's looks not bad.
# 嗯
Um!
# 可以
Not bad!
# 很不錯哦
It's really quite good.
# 有點那種
It has a sort of like,
# 那種澀澀的
like an astringent
# 澀澀的感覺
astringent taste,
# 還有
and a,
# 里面有蛋香味
a scent of eggs,
# 雞蛋的蛋
I mean chicken eggs.
# 很好吃
It's really tasty.
# 這個太老啦
It's too old.
# 如果
If,
# 再過
after,
# 提前 提前半個月
if we came two weeks, two weeks earlier
# 我把來摘來吃 就比較嫩一點
it would be younger and much more tender.
# 不過還不老
But it's still not really old.
# 還沒完全開花
It has not yet completely blossomed.
# 嗯
Um!
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.